Tyler Skorczewski

Contact Department of Mathematics, Statistics,

Information & Computer Science

University of Wisconsin Stout Office Phone: (715) 232- 5392

Office: Jarvis Hall Science Wing 311 Dept. Fax: () -

410 10th Ave E E-mail: skorczewskit@uwstout.edu

Menomonie, WI 54751

CITIZENSHIP United States

SCHOLARLY Interests My scholarly interests revolve around developing mathematics that can be used to understand problems arising in biological and industrial settings and incorporating insights gleaned from this work into an effective program of undergraduate applied mathematics education and research.

EDUCATION University of California, Davis, California, USA

Ph.D., Applied Mathematics, September 2010

Thesis Topic: A computational fluid dynamics study of suction feeding fish using

Chimera overset grids

Adviser: Professor Angela Cheer

University of Wisconsin Oshkosh, Oshkosh, WI

B.S., Mathematics and Physics, May 2004

Thesis Topic: Characterization of surface roughness through fractal dimension

Magna cum Laude

ACADEMIC Assistant Professor 2017

APPOINTMENTS

Department of Mathematics, Statistics, & Computer Science,

University of Wisconsin Stout

Assistant Professor 2014 to 2017

Department of Mathematics & Statistics,

Cornell College

Research Assistant Professor 2010 to 2014

Department of Mathematics,

University of Utah

TEACHING University of Wisconsin Stout

Experience Department of Mathematics, Statistics & Computer Science

Faculty 2017 to present

Courses: Math 123 Finite and Financial Math; Math 154 Calculus II for Engineers; Math 157 Calculus and Analytic Geometry II; Math 250 Differential Equations and Linear Algebra; Math 90 Intermediate Algebra (online); Math 275 Linear Algebra; Math 150 Calculus with Precalculus I; MSCS 496 Preparation for Industrial Careers in Mathematics

Cornell College

Department of Mathematics & Statistics

Faculty 2014 to 2017

Courses: MAT 221 Linear Algebra; MAT 119/120 Single Variable Calculus w precalculus; MAT 236 Differential Equations; MAT 317 Mathematical Modeling; MAT 122 Multivariable Calculus; MAT 361 Advanced Topics: Scientific Computation; MAT 121 Single Variable Calculus; STA 201 Statistical Methods; MAT 256 Mathematical Models in Biology; MAT 357 Preparations for Industrial Careers (PIC) Math; MAT 358 Partial Differential Equations

Organized courses, lessons, activities, exams and oversaw all administrative responsibilities

Implemented a resigned Math major curriculum including an innovative Culture Points program

Implemented a new Applied Math minor

University of Utah

Department of Mathematics

Instructor 2010 to 2014

Courses: Math 1320 Engineering Calculus II; Math 2250 Differential Equations and Linear Algebra (\times 2); Math 1220 Calculus II

Organized courses, lectures, exams and oversaw all administrative responsibilities including teaching assistants

Involved in the development and implementation of new Engineering Math sequence/curriculum

University of California, Davis

Department of Evolution and Ecology

Teaching Assistant/Fellow

2009 to 2010

Collaborative Learning at the Interface of Mathematics and Biology (CLIMB) Program

A one year research-training program in mathematical biology for UC Davis students in mathematical sciences or biology.

I assisted in the mentoring of several scholarship undergraduate students in learning the concepts behind mathematical modeling and analysis in different biological fields and helped them to formulate their own research project. Aided them in their pursuit of their research project: modeling the effects of kin recognition and supercolony formation in Argentine ants.

Department of Mathematics

 $Associate\ Instructor$

Summer Session II 2009

MAT 21D: Vector Analysis

Organized course, gave lectures and exams, held office hours and oversaw all administrative responsibilities

Teaching Assistant

2005 to 2009

Courses: MAT 17A/17B/17C Calculus for Biology and Medicine; MAT 128A/B/C Undergraduate Numerical Analysis; MAT 228A/228B Graduate Numerical Solutions for Partial Differential Equations

Led discussion sections, held office hours, and graded papers and exams.

University of Wisconsin Oshkosh

Department of Physics

Teaching Assistant 2003 to 2004

Held office hours in support of all undergraduate physics classes

Industry Positions

Research/Scientist Intern

2003 to 2004

Kimberly-Clark Corporation Neenah, WI

Performed research in areas of sensor physics, surface physics, and fluid dynamics in porous media under the direction of senior research staff in the Analytical and Measurement Technologies and Mathematical Modeling departments with the goal of developing innovative consumer products.

Software Engineer

2004 to 2005

Epic Systems Corporation Madison, WI

Developed electronic medical record software focusing on scheduling and radiology departments.

UG RESEARCH ADVISING

Ben DeViney

2013

Ben worked on an REU during the Spring of 2013 concering the fluid dynamics of suction feeding on multiple prey items. This work has produced one journal article thus far.

Jake Lehman, Jordan Wolfe, & Brian Cristion

2014

Jake, Jordan, and Brian used a markov chain approach to measure competitive balance in sports leagues in a way that allows comparisons across sports. This groups work was presented at the 2015 MAA Mathfest.

Josh Lee 2015

Josh explored the relationship between jaw kinematics of suction feeding fish and the resulting fluid flow patterns using a computational method called the immersed boundary method. This was part of the 2015 Cornell Institute for Summer Research.

Sam Cieszynski 2016

Sam created a model forest fires using cellular automata and analyzed his results using fractal geometry and statistical mechanics concepts as part of the 2016 Cornell Institute for Summer Research.

Drew Klocke 2016

Drew analyzed the relationship between the size of NCAA division I basketball conferences and the differences found among various intraconference rating and ranking schemes. Drew presented this work at the 2016 Midwest Sports Analytics Conference.

Kasper Kittredge

2017

Kas investigated learning models in youth archery including such varied approaches as descriptive/inferntial statistics, differential equations, discrete dynamical systems and time series analysis. This work was presented at the Joint Math Meetings January 2018 in San Diego.

Brandon Anderson

2018

Brandon worked with me to develop a dynamic energy budget theory of turtle sheel growth. He will present at the 2018 UW Stout STEM Fesitval.

JOURNAL ARTICLES

- Skorczewski, T., Cheer, A., Cheung, S., Wainwright, P.: Use of computational fluid dynamics to study forces on prey by aquatic suction feeders. Journal of the Royal Society Interface (2009).
- Skorczewski, T., Cheer, A., Wainwright, P.: The benefits of planar circular mouths on suction feeding performance. Journal of the Royal Society Interface (2012).
- Skorczewski, T., Crowl, L., Fogelson, A.L.: Platelet motion near a vessel wall or thrombus surface in 2D whole blood simulations. Biophysical Journal (2013).
- Skorczewski, T. Griffith, B., Fogelson, A.L.: Multi-bond models of platelet adhesion and cohesion. Biological Fluid Dynamics: Modeling, Computations, and Applications. AMS Contemporary Mathematics Series (2014).
- DeViney, B., Skorczewski, T.: Suction feeding on multiple prey. J Roy Soc Interface (submitted).
- Van Wassenbergh, S, Day, S.W., Hernandez, L.P., Higham, T.E., Skorczewski, T.:: Suction power output and the inertial cost of accelerating the neurocranium to generate suction in fish. Journal of Theoretical Biology. (2015).
- Walton, B.L., Lehmann, M., Skorczewski, T., Beckman, J.D., Holle, L.A., Cribb, J.A., Mooberry, M.J., Wufsus, A.R., Cooley, B.C., Homeister, J.W., Falvo, M.R., Fogelson, A.L., Neeves, K.B., Wolberg, A.S. Elevated hematocrit promotes arterial thrombosis. Blood (2017).
- Bernstein, N.P., Todd, R., Baloch, M.Y., McCollum, A., Skorczewski, T., Mickael, K.A., Eastham, J.E.M. Morphometric Models of Growth in Ornate Box Turtles (*Terrapene ornata ornata*) as Related to Growth Rings. Chelonian Conservation and Biology (2018).
- Skorczewski, T. Modeling Learning in Youth Archery. Mathematical Gazette. (submit 2019).

Conference Proceedings Skorczewski, T., Richard, G., Proctor, W., Shen, C., Wang, M., Zhang, J., Zhong, P., Smith, R., Massad, J.: Design of rf mems switches without pull-in instability. In: Proceedings of SPIE, Smart Structures and Materials. San Diego, CA (2010).

TECHNICAL REPORTS

- Skorczewski, T., Richard, G., Proctor, W., Shen, C., Wang, M., Zhang, J., Zhong, P., Smith, R., Massad, J.: Design of rf mems switches without pull-in instability. IMSM Workshop, North Carolina State University. (2009).
- Hendriks, F., Rubin, K., Cargill, D., Fehribach, J., Lin, T-S., Please, C., Raymond, C.,
 Schwendeman, D., Skorczewski, T., Tilley, B., Witelski, T., Wrobel J., Wang, J., Zhang,
 S.: Homogenization of the equations governing the flow between a slider bearing and a rough spinning disk. Mathematical Problems in Industry, University of Delaware. (2009).
- Subbarayappa, D.A., Johnson, D., Skorczewski, T., Hibdon, J., Lin, T-S., Cargill, D., Cummings, L. Bistable nematic liquid crystal devices. GSMMC, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute. (2009).

Grants & Funded Awards NSF/MAA PIC (Preparation for Industrial Careers) (2018)

UW Stout First Year Program funding (2018)

UW Stout Start-up funds (2017)

- Associated Colleges of the Midwest Seminars in Advanced Interdisciplinary Learning (ACM SAIL) (2017)
- Leadership team for ACM FaCE grant "Engaging the Community of Mathematicians" (\$17,600) (2017)

Cornell College Institute for Summer Research (2017)

NSF/MAA PIC (Preparation for Industrial Careers) (2016)

Cornell College Institute for Summer Research (2016)

NSF Travel award to present at Computational Biofluids in Physiology Conference (2015)

Cornell College Institute for Summer Research (2015)

Cornell College course development funds for Scientific Computing (2015)

MAA Project NExT (2014-2015)

University of Utah Mariott Library Open Access Publishing Fund (2013)

University of Utah NSF VIGRE REU support for Ben DeViney (2013)

Travel award NIMBioS Workshop on blood clotting (2013)

Member of NIMBioS Working Group on suction feeding mechanics (2012-2013)

University of Utah Center for High Performance Computing allocation (2012-2013,2013-2014)

University of Utah Center for High Performance Computing quick allocation (2012)

University of California Davis minigrant for SIAM Student Research Conference (2008,2009)

Society of Industrial and Applied Mathematics student group award (2007,2008)

REFEREE SERVICE

Journal of Theoretical Biology

Integrative and Comparative Biology

Journal of Computational Methods in Sciences and Engineering

University/ College Service

Educational Activities Committee

UW Stout2018-2021

Colloquium Committee

UW Stout 2017-2018

Organized talks for the MSCS department

Rise Up program mentor

Cornell College 2016-2017

Mentor for first-generation college students from diverse backgrounds.

Academic Affairs Committee

Cornell College 2015-2017

STEM Fair coordinator

Cedar Rapids Public Library/Kirkwood Regional Center 2015-2017

Organized students and faculty to represent Cornell College at the Cedar Rapids Public Library STEM Fairs in 2015 and 2016.

Problem of the Block Contest Organizer

Cornell College. 2014-present

Organized and administered the Problem of the Block contest in the Department of Mathematics & Statistics at Cornell College.

Math Club Advisor

Cornell College. 2014-present

Organized and advised the Math Club at Cornell College.

LATEX Workshop

Cornell College. 2014

Led a workshop to introduce students to LATEX, a mathematical typesetting language.

Calculus Carnival

University of Utah, 2012,2013

This math department event is held every semester and uses games such as Math Jeopardy and Calculus Pictionary to teach calculus and precalculus concepts.

Maple and Matlab Introductory Sessions

University of Utah, 2010,2012

Organized and taught workshops introducing undergraduate students to Maple and Matlab software.

SIAM Club Executive Chairman

University of California, Davis, 2007–2009

Chaired the five member executive committee for the Society of Industrial and Applied Mathematics (SIAM) club at UC Davis which promotes applied mathematics throughout the UC Davis campus and provides a forum for students interested in applied mathematics. Organized the first and second annual Davis SIAM Student Research Conferences which highlight the cutting edge applied mathematics research being performed by students at UC Davis and included several keynote addresses. Successfully orchestrated SIAM funding grant and NSF VIGRE grant proposals to fund projects.

OTHER

Judge

SERVICE

SIAM M³ Contest (2017)

JMM Undergraduate Poster Competition (2015)

Salt Lake Valley Regional Science and Engineering Fair (2011-2014)

Eastern Iowa Science and Engineering Fair (2016)

Mathematics Volunteer

Wasatch Elementary School, Salt Lake City, UT (2010-2012)

Awards and Honors

Robert F. Witte Project NExT Fellow

Mathematical Association of America (MAA) (2014-2015)

Exceptional Service Award

Society of Industrial and Applied Mathematics (SIAM) (2009)

Harvey McKensie Math Award

Department of Mathematics, UW Oshkosh (2004)

Knop Physics Scholar

Ripon College, Ripon, WI (2000-2001)

Hornigold Science Award

Lincoln High School, Wisconsin Rapids, WI (2000)

SELECTED TALKS AND

Modeling Learning in Youth Archery, UW Stout MSCS Department Colloquium, October 19, 2018.

Presentations

A dynamic energy budget model of ornate box turtle shell growth, MAA Mathfest, Denver, CO, August 3, 2018.

Sports Analytics in Youth Archery, MAA Wisconsin Section Meeting, Eau Claire, WI, April 6, 2018.

- Exploring how students learn in youth archery, Joint Math Meetings, San Diego, January 11, 2018.
- Mathematical models in blood clotting, UW Oshkosh Math Department Colloquium, November 10, 2017; Cornell College Colloquium April 4, 2018; UW Stout MSCS Department Colloquium April 20, 2018.
- Mathematical models of learning in youth archery, Coe College Colloquium Series, January 24, 2017.
- Modeling learning in youth archery, Joint Math Meetings, Atlanta, January 6, 2017.
- Growth Rate of Ornate Box Turtles in East-Central Iowa, IAAS, 2016.
- A New Way to Measure Competitive Balance Across Sports Leagues, MAA Mathfest, Washington DC, August 6, 2015.
- Multibond models of platelet adhesion, Computational Biofluids in Physiology, University of Utah, Salt Lake City, May 14-15, 2015.
- Toward an integrative model of suction feeding using the immersed boundary method, Mathematical Biology Seminar, University of Iowa, May 4, 2015.
- The math and science of suction feeding, Cornell College, February 25, 2015.
- Toward an integrative model of suction feeding using the immersed boundary method, 2014 Iowa MAA Meeting, Clarke University, October 24, 2014.
- Multibond models of platelet adhesion, Joint Math Meetings, Baltimore, MD, January 10, 2014.
- Investigating suction feeding using the immersed boundary method, NIMBioS, Knoxville, TN, May 21, 2013.
- Investigating blood clotting using the immersed boundary method, University of Wisconsin LaCrosse, February 6, 2013.
- Design of RF MEMS switches without pull-in instability, Davis SIAM Student Research Conference, Davis, CA, May 8, 2010.
- Design of RF MEMS switches without pull-in instability, SPIE Smart Structures, San Diego, CA, March 10, 2010.
- Using computational fluid dynamics to study fish suction feeding, Merck Pharmaceuticals, West Point, PA, February 25, 2010.
- Using computational fluid dynamics to study fish suction feeding and the design of RF MEMS switches, Sandia National Labs, February 9, 2010.
- Homogenization of the Equations Governing the Flow Between a Slider and a Rough Spinning Disk, MPI 2009, University of Delaware, June 19, 2009.
- Bistable liquid crystal display design, GSMMC, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, June 12, 2009.
- Unsteady computational fluid dynamics of fish suction feeding on stationary prey, Society of Integrative and Comparative Biology Annual Meeting, San Antonio, January 6, 2008.
- Characterization of surface roughness through fractal dimension, Physics Seminar, University of Wisconsin Oshkosh, April 21, 2004.
- Relating fractal dimension of surface roughness to manufacturing processes, Kimberly-Clark, Neenah, WI, January 8, 2004.

Validation of absorbency finite element analysis in 3 dimensions, Kimberly-Clark, Neenah, WI, August 12, 2003.

Calibration and uses of flexible arrays of capacititance based pressure sensors, Kimberly-Clark, Neenah, WI, May 23, 2003.